<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Flores regij. Or, prouerbes and aphorismes, diuine and morall. As they were at seuerall times vpon sundry occasions, spoken / by his most excellent Maiestie, Iames, of famous memory King of Great-Brittaine. ; Collected by I.L.S.</title>
            <author>James I, King of England, 1566-1625.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1627</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 89 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04256</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14375</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107606</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843304</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843304</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8022</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04256)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8022)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 739:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Flores regij. Or, prouerbes and aphorismes, diuine and morall. As they were at seuerall times vpon sundry occasions, spoken / by his most excellent Maiestie, Iames, of famous memory King of Great-Brittaine. ; Collected by I.L.S.</title>
                  <author>James I, King of England, 1566-1625.</author>
                  <author>I. L. S., fl. 1627.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 171, [1] p. : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by B[ernard] A[lsop] and T[homas] F[awcet] for Ben: Fisher,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1627.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation from the English.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  I, --  King of England, 1566-1625 --  Quotations.</term>
               <term>Aphorisms and apothegms.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8022:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8022:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Flores Regij.</hi> OR, PROVERBES AND APHORISMES, DIVINE AND MORALL. As they were at ſeuerall times vpon ſundry occaſions, <hi>Spoken by his Most Excellent</hi> MAIESTIE, IAMES, of famous Memory King of <hi>Great-Brittaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Collected by <hi>J. L. S.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>B. A.</hi> and <hi>T. F.</hi> for <hi>Ben: Fiſher.</hi> 1627.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="proverbs">
            <pb facs="tcp:8022:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:8022:2"/>
            <head>Flores Regij. PROVERBES AND APHORISMES, DIVINE AND MORALL.</head>
            <p n="1">1. <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>ORDES are not the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of good men and bad,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:8022:3"/>for euery man ſpeakes, therefore how noble a thing is <hi>Vertue;</hi> when no man dares profeſſe any thing.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I loue not one that will neuer bee Angry: For as hee that is without <hi>Sorrow,</hi> is without <hi>Gladneſſe:</hi> ſo hee that is without
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:8022:3"/>
               <hi>Anger,</hi> is without <hi>Loue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. There are De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of men in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in reſpect of GOD all are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall, all are to vſe like Dutie, like Reuerence, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him: All are alike beggers at Gods doore.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:8022:4"/>
            <p n="4">4. Wee are depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted noe further from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> then they from their firſt IESVS.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Giue mee the heart of a <hi>Man,</hi> and out of that all other his deeds ſhall bee accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:8022:4"/>
            <p n="6">6. In Cloathes, I would haue a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion ſhould chuſe a man, and not a man the faſhion.</p>
            <p n="7">7. It is one of the miſeries of <hi>Man,</hi> that when hee is full of dayes, and neere his end, that then hee ſhould Loue life moſt.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:8022:5"/>
            <p n="8">8. It hath like o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration, to make <hi>Women</hi> Learned, as to make <hi>Foxes</hi> tame, which tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth them onely to ſteale more cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly. The poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibilitie is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall, for where it doth one good it doth twentie harme.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:8022:5"/>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>Parents</hi> may for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid their Children an vnfit match, but they may not force their conſent to a fit.</p>
            <p n="10">10. No Countrie can be called <hi>Rich</hi> wherein there is <hi>Warre;</hi> As in the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> there is much money,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:8022:6"/>but the Souldiers haue it in Pay from the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, the Boores haue it for victuals of the Soldiers, the Gouernours haue it from them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in taxes: So there is no Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, no Honour.</p>
            <p n="11">11. No man gaines by <hi>Warre,</hi> but hee
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:8022:6"/>that hath not wherewith to Liue in <hi>Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. God accepts the intent before the deed, for if a Man doe <hi>Iuſtice</hi> becauſe he would bee Counted juſt, and not for Gods glorie, not becauſe hee ſtands anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to GOD, if
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:8022:7"/>hee doe otherwiſe, or if hee puniſh a man rightly, but withall ſatisfie his owne mallice; both theſe are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable: if hee giue Almes onely for his reputation ſake, this is a wicked Deed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is <hi>Nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum medium,</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is not of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:8022:7"/>Faith is ſinne.</p>
            <p n="13">13. No man ſhall doe ill, that thinks ere he vndertakes, what the end will bee, not what his paſſion would haue it to be.</p>
            <p n="14">14. <hi>Time</hi> is the eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of manie Lawes, ſo that a <hi>King</hi> may do well
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:8022:8"/>at diuers times, both in making and abrogating the ſame <hi>Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">15. I ſhould thinke it a ſigne that GOD loues mee not, if I ſhould kill a man by chance, I would moſt vnwillingly doe that ill, which it lyes not in my
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:8022:8"/>power to amend.</p>
            <p n="16">16. I doe not thinke the greateſt Clerkes are neareſt Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, much of their knowledge is ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous; For BELLARMINE makes 400. queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Faith,</hi> and not tenne of them which toucheth
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:8022:9"/>our Saluation to vnderſtand.</p>
            <p n="17">17. Many haue at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to make Glaſſe malleable, and ſo Gold arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall, but both in vaine; for GOD doth euer croſſe the inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Man,</hi> leaſt hee ſhould reioyce in his owne worke.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:8022:9"/>
            <p n="18">18. The perſons of all men are to be alike. Equall to vs, and our <hi>Hate</hi> or Loue, ſhould onely goe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues</hi> or <hi>Vices.</hi> Theſe bonds of kindred ſhould onely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund vs in all Ciuill duties, but not our iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:8022:10"/>And par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler iniuries ſhould onely make vs hate that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler deede, but not the Doer in generall.</p>
            <p n="19">19. <hi>Men</hi> of high vnderſtanding as they doe many things aboue the Common ſtraine: So they often fall
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:8022:10"/>into greater er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, then thoſe of meaner Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie, which in all their Actions, will rather doe nothing faultie, then any thing extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry being of a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per better mixt then the former.</p>
            <p n="20">20. The Deuill al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies auoydes the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:8022:11"/>meane, and waites vpon extremities; So hath he ſought to deuide the world betwixt <hi>Athiſme,</hi> and <hi>Superſtition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="21">21. All extremities come round to one end, the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple obedience of the <hi>Papiſt,</hi> and the no obedience of the <hi>Puritaine,</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:8022:11"/>the one breeds Confuſion, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Ignorance and Securitie.</p>
            <p n="22">22. The end of the <hi>Lawe,</hi> is to puniſh ſinne when it is Committed, But to keepe it from being Committed it cannot; As the <hi>Pope</hi> which thinks by allowing <hi>Forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:8022:12"/>to auoyd <hi>Adulterie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="23">23. The wiſedome of a King is chiefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeene in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, as in places which require a peculiar ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, not to chuſe them that hee af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects moſt, but to vſe euery man ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:8022:12"/>to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per fitnes.</p>
            <p n="24">24. <hi>Vertue</hi> is eaſier then <hi>Vice,</hi> for the eſſentiall difference betwixt <hi>Vice</hi> and <hi>Vertue,</hi> is <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Falſhood:</hi> And it is eaſier and leſſe paines to tell truth then a lye: And for vices of the ſences, <hi>Cuſtome</hi> is
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:8022:13"/>all in all; for to one that hath liued honeſtly, it is aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much paine to Commit ſinne, as for another to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine</p>
            <p n="25">25. It is likely that the people will imitate the King in good, but it is ſure they will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him in ill.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:8022:13"/>
            <p n="26">26. I haue beene often deceiued, yet will I neuer leaue to truſt; neither ſhall the falſehood of ſome, make me think there is none honeſt.</p>
            <p n="27">27. All that euer writ of CHRIST, ſaid, hee was an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man, they had
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:8022:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:8022:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:8022:15"/>ſo much naturall ſight as to ſee his Ciuill goodneſſe, but they wanted the ſupernaturall to perceiue his God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head.</p>
            <p n="28">28. The ſame ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence with diuers Relations may be both Holy and Diueliſh.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:8022:15"/>
            <p n="29">29. I wonder not ſo much that <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> paint them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, as that when they are painted men can Loue them.</p>
            <p n="30">30. Of all the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of men, that haue beene ſlaine in the Warre, not the tenth part haue
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:8022:16"/>beene fighting but flying.</p>
            <p n="31">31. PARSONS erres in his reſolution, in making the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie of our <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation,</hi> to lye in the hardnes to finde Gods mercy; when indeed, it conſiſts onely in the right ſeeking of it; for then the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:8022:16"/>other is ſure.</p>
            <p n="32">32. God hath deſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted his benefits ſo equally, that there is no Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie which excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth not all other in ſome thing, ſo that as it bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roweth ſo it len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth: So in men, there is no one excelleth ſo in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:8022:17"/>one thing, but hath neede of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wit in ſome other; From theſe two proceeds all Traffique and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie.</p>
            <p n="33">33. The Art of <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicions</hi> is very im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect, for I doubt not but for euery Diſeaſe, there is in Nature a ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:8022:17"/>
               <hi>ſimple,</hi> if they could finde it out: So that their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds doe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhowe their ignorance, then their knowledge.</p>
            <p n="34">34. The Deuill where hee cannot haue the whole, ſeekes euer to get one part of the <hi>Soule,</hi> either the <hi>Will</hi> or
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:8022:18"/>the <hi>Vnderſtanding,</hi> which hee may come eaſieſt by; as in <hi>Proteſtants</hi> the the <hi>Will,</hi> in <hi>Papiſts</hi> the <hi>Vnderſtanding:</hi> A learned Papiſt and an ignorant, are of two Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions.</p>
            <p n="35">35. The <hi>Papiſts</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is like HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MERS <hi>Illiades</hi> of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:8022:18"/>the ſeige of <hi>Troy,</hi> or VIRGILS <hi>Aeneods</hi> of the beginning of <hi>Rome,</hi> both of them had a foundation of truth, ſo had the Papiſts the Bible: But they haue all added ſo much, that the firſt Truth is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt loſt.</p>
            <p n="36">36. GOD neuer
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:8022:19"/>failes of his word, but where hee threateneth ill to <hi>Man,</hi> as in puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Niniuie,</hi> but alwayes performes where hee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth good, that, or better, as hee promiſed to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BRAHAM and his ſeede, euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting earthly bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe, and in
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:8022:19"/>ſtead of that, gaue them <hi>Heauenly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="37">37. Not onely the Deliuerance of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> till they came to the Land of Promiſe, but euen their Dayly preſeruation was miraculous: for, there was neuer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny noted Plague in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> though
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:8022:20"/>it ſtood in a hot Climate, which had it beene, would haue endangered the whole Nation, it beeing to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble thither twiſe euery yeare of neceſſitie.</p>
            <p n="38">38. Men are often in arguing, carried by the force of wordes further a
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:8022:20"/>ſunder, then their queſtion was at firſt, like two <hi>Ships</hi> going out of the ſame hauen, their Iournies end is many times whole Countries diſtant.</p>
            <p n="39">39. <hi>Cowardize</hi> is the mother of <hi>Crueltie;</hi> It was onely <hi>Feare,</hi> that made <hi>Tyrants</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:8022:21"/>put ſo many to death, to ſecure themſelues.</p>
            <p n="40">40. That faſhion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Romaines</hi> of killing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, was falſely called <hi>Fortitude,</hi> for, it was onely to preuent the power of <hi>Fortune;</hi> when indeed, <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue</hi> lies within
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:8022:21"/>quite out of her reach. Nor can any man be ouercome but of himſelfe: And ſo moſt true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly were they, when they fled to Death for a refuge againſt Death.</p>
            <p n="41">41. It is eaſier to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime a man from any Hereſie, then to Conuert an <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thieſt</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:8022:22"/>to the <hi>Truth:</hi> For to beleeue, is the firſt Degree Common to all Religions: And an <hi>Athieſt</hi> is to bee brought ſo farre, before he come to chuſing.</p>
            <p n="42">42. All Gods mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles are aboue Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but neuer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Nature, for
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:8022:22"/>that were to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy his owne worke, which he cannot doe, but he may excell it: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the miracle of the <hi>Papiſts Trans ſubſtantiation</hi> being againſt <hi>Nature,</hi> is falſe.</p>
            <p n="43">43. <hi>Types</hi> are the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages of the mind, which God allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:8022:23"/>the <hi>Iewes</hi> to keepe them from <hi>Images</hi> of the ſence, and to ſhew them, that his worſhip was to be in Spirit and Truth.</p>
            <p n="44">44. The Church at <hi>Rome,</hi> fell at firſt from her puritie into <hi>Infirmities,</hi> then into <hi>Corruptions,</hi> then into <hi>Errours;</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:8022:23"/>and laſtly, into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominations. GOD ſtill puniſhing Sin with ſinne.</p>
            <p n="45">45. Moſt Hereſies haue proceeded, from mingling <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophie</hi> with <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion;</hi> from that and <hi>pollicie,</hi> haue all the <hi>Papiſt</hi> er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours riſen: when CHRIST tels
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:8022:24"/>them, that fleſh and blood cannot inherite the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</p>
            <p n="46">46. Wee cannot conceiue Eternitie but by <hi>Faith,</hi> wee cannot vnderſtand what GOD is; and of that igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance comes all ſinne, for ſurely
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:8022:24"/>if wee knew him, wee would not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend him.</p>
            <p n="47">47. Men as often fall out about ſmall things as great, becauſe after the firſt contradiction, they mainetaine themſelues not the thing.</p>
            <p n="48">48. Before CHRIST
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:8022:25"/>came, it was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> to beleeue on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſince they muſt beleeue and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand both.</p>
            <p n="49">49. Thoſe <hi>Princes,</hi> which ſeeke to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure themſelues by blood; ſhall finde, that the more they kill, the more they haue needs to kill.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:8022:25"/>
            <p n="50">50. The <hi>Church</hi> is to bee beleeued, in the interpretation of the <hi>Scripture,</hi> but not directly againſt it; for when it dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers from that, it is no longer the <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="51">51. There are three kindes of <hi>Wiſedomes</hi> that vſe to bee in
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:8022:26"/>
               <hi>Kings,</hi> A ſanctified <hi>Wiſedome,</hi> A <hi>Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> which often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſtraines it ſelfe to a leſſe euill, ſo to auoyde a greater, and a <hi>Wiſedome</hi> of falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood; the firſt, is both lawfull and neceſſarie; the ſecond, is lawfull, but not neceſſarie; the third, neither.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:8022:26"/>
            <p n="52">52. All Gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments howſoeuer in their Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, in their practize tend to a <hi>Monarchie;</hi> And whereſoeuer the better ſort of the people beare rule, there is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſome one that reſembleth a <hi>King</hi> amongſt
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:8022:27"/>them: yea? though in the <hi>State</hi> of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice,</hi> the <hi>Duke</hi> is but as it were a dead name; yet were it impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that their Common-wealth ſhould long vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold it ſelfe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him.</p>
            <p n="53">53. The preſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Bible,</hi> is
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:8022:27"/>miraculous, that it ſhould remaine pure, and intyre, after it had paſſed the hands of Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels which ſought to deſtroy it, of Heritiques which ſought to peruert it, to their owne aduantage.</p>
            <p n="54">54. No indifferent geſture, is ſo ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:8022:28"/>dome done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſinne, as <hi>laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> for, it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly raiſed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on things to bee pittied; And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Man</hi> onely can laugh, and he onely can ſinne.</p>
            <p n="55">55. GOD made one part of <hi>Man</hi> of earth, the baſeſt element, to teach
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:8022:28"/>him <hi>Humilitie,</hi> his Soule proceeded from the boſome of himſelfe, to teach him <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes:</hi> So that if hee looke downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, nothing is viler: if hee caſt his eyes to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, hee is of a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter more excellent then the <hi>Angells;</hi> the former part,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:8022:29"/>was a type of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DAM; the ſecond, of CHRIST, which giues life to that, which was dead in it ſelfe.</p>
            <p n="56">56. Much money makes a Countrie poore, for it ſets a dearer price vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on euery thing.</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:8022:29"/>
            <p n="57">57. At what time the <hi>Goſpell</hi> did flouriſh, all kinde of Learning did e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen abound, and vpon the decay thereof, there came alwayes a vaile of darkenes vpon the face of the earth: The reaſon is a part of <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> but Errour
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:8022:30"/>and Superſtition, is the ſafer by Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance.</p>
            <p n="58">58. A lye of errour, is a fault of Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulitie, not of falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood; But a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous lye, is that which a man makes, as GOD made the world of nothing.</p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:8022:30"/>
            <p n="59">59. All Gods Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are for our good, either Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually, or Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally although wee cannot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend them at euery time.</p>
            <p n="60">60. There is not that thing vpon the earth, (that well examined)
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:8022:31"/>yeilds not ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what worthie of knowledge; That <hi>Diuine Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>izan</hi> that made them, neuer faſhioned any thing vnprofitably, nor euer ſet forth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhippe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome inward Vertue.</p>
            <p n="61">61. The guifts of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:8022:31"/>the minde are not eaſily obtained, you muſt practiſe them with great paine, and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie, and good reaſon; for it were pittie ſuch preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, might be had for the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king.</p>
            <p n="62">62. It muſt needes ſhew the <hi>Papiſts</hi>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:8022:32"/>Religion to be ill, that they would plant it by <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> and <hi>Warre;</hi> whereas the <hi>true Catholique Religion,</hi> roſe by <hi>Faſting</hi> and <hi>Prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="63">63. Whatſoeuer is ſpent in earthly vanities, they ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dye before vs, or ſhortly follow
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:8022:32"/>after vs, for all pleaſures that are ſenſuall, and haue not reference to the maine end of mans <hi>Creation,</hi> (which is the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of GOD) are vaine and of no importance, but meere foolerie.</p>
            <p n="64">64. When GOD deſtinates a man
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:8022:33"/>to doe good, hee makes euery opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie and occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (though it ſeem neuer ſo harſh in mans eyes) to turne to his good and GODS glorie; But when GOD leaues man to himſelfe, hee makes more oportunities then hee findes, and without occaſion
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:8022:33"/>takes occaſion to worke his owne ruine to his owne ſhame.</p>
            <p n="65">65. It is good to propound a man <hi>Fame, Greatnes, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor,</hi> and <hi>Eſtimation,</hi> for wading to find theſe, hee may happily meete with <hi>Honeſtie, Temporance, Fortitude</hi> and <hi>Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:8022:34"/>And many times they that will not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe Actions for <hi>Vertues</hi> ſake, will for <hi>Ambition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="66">66. An ill name may be free from Diſhoneſtie, but not from ſome follie; we ſhould not onely be free from ſinne, but
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:8022:34"/>from ſuſpition, for it is not enough to bee well Liued, but well repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times weightie matters are aſmuch carried by repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation as ſubſtance.</p>
            <p n="67">67. <hi>Misfortunes</hi> are not acceptable in any kinde, yet
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:8022:35"/>thoſe are indured with moſt eaſe, that come rather by deſtinie, then by deſeruing.</p>
            <p n="68">68. In expence it is good to bee nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pinching nor prodigall, yet if meanes allowe it, rather thought a little profuſe then too ſparing, but
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:8022:35"/>the beſt way is, to make abilitie (which muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes bee meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, by the iuſt Rule of our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Reuenue) our compaſſe, to ſaile, and lyne, to walke by, And for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, wee muſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them by the worth of the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:8022:36"/>for in matters that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne not, wee may bee more magnificent.</p>
            <p n="69">69. Hee is not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to <hi>Command</hi> others, that cannot gouerne his owne affections and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites.</p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:8022:36"/>
            <p n="70">70. No text of <hi>Law</hi> can be ſo certaine; wherein, the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances will not make a varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="71">71. <hi>Iuſtice</hi> ſhould bee blinde, and friendleſſe, it is not by it, that, thoſe that are in authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, ſhould Reward
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:8022:37"/>their friends, or Croſſe their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
            <p n="72">72. Though out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Peace bee a great bleſſing, yet it is farre in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour to Peace within, as Ciuill warres are more cruell and vnnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall then warres abroad.</p>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:8022:37"/>
            <p n="73">73. All <hi>Vertues</hi> turne to <hi>Vices,</hi> when they become the ſeruants of impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie.</p>
            <p n="74">74. All Complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners bee natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally giuen to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agerate their owne griefes and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplyes thereupon, As Papiſts doe
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:8022:38"/>in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="75">75. As a thing which is good ought not therefore to bee abuſed, ſo ought not the Lawfulnes of a good thing be forborne, becauſe of the abuſe therof.</p>
            <p n="76">76. Euery <hi>Man</hi> ought to diſcerne wiſely and truely of euery
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:8022:38"/>
               <hi>Vertue</hi> and <hi>Vice,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the true qualities thereof, and not according to the vaine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits of men.</p>
            <p n="77">77. Indifferent things if they be neceſſary, as food, ſleepe, and ſuch like, in the qua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lities or forme of v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, may ſmell of <hi>Vertue</hi> or <hi>Vice,</hi>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:8022:39"/>and bee great fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers to any of them.</p>
            <p n="78">78. If our whole life were deuided into foure parts, three of them would bee found to bee conſumed, on <hi>Meate, Drinke, Sleepe,</hi> and vnne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:8022:39"/>
            <p n="79">79. There is great Difference betwixt <hi>Iuſtice</hi> and <hi>Equitie,</hi> for <hi>Iuſtice</hi> by the <hi>Law,</hi> giueth euery <hi>Man</hi> his owne, and <hi>Equitie</hi> in things Arbitriall, that which is mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt for him.</p>
            <p n="80">80. Drunkenneſſe is a beaſtly <hi>Vice,</hi> and
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:8022:40"/>hath this proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that it is one of thoſe <hi>Vices</hi> that increaſeth with age.</p>
            <p n="81">81. <hi>Medecine</hi> hath that <hi>Vertue,</hi> that it neuer leaues a Man in that ſtate wherein it findes him.</p>
            <p n="82">82. Wee ſhould
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:8022:40"/>preſſe to winne GOD by impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie; if wee ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine not at the firſt, and if wee bee not heard, ſhould thinke, that that which wee ſeeke is not for our good.</p>
            <p n="83">83. A ſmall ſinne wilfully commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, is farre more
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:8022:41"/>grieuous before GOD, then a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter committed in a ſuddaine paſſion, when Conſcience is a ſleepe.</p>
            <p n="84">84. The thing one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly which without intermiſſion, wee are bidden to doe, is to <hi>Pray:</hi> For as for other things they haue their
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:8022:41"/>owne time, but <hi>Prayer</hi> is neuer out of ſeaſon.</p>
            <p n="85">85. Wee ſhould not bee like the <hi>Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines</hi> in our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, who ſpeake to GOD as to their fellowes: and ſit at CHRISTS table, as with their Companions, Let vs ioyne reuerence
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:8022:42"/>with the ſweete confidence wee haue in GODS Loue.</p>
            <p n="86">86. Bread without the ſtaffe of bread, which is Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, is no bread; For without this, euen although it be in our mouthes, wee ſhall die for <hi>Hunger,</hi> like the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:8022:42"/>rich man, that in his grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt abundance of all things, dyed for want.</p>
            <p n="87">87. Wee pray in vaine, GOD to ſaue vs, from temptation, if at euery occaſion we runne vnto it: Like one who volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily ſtickes in the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:8022:43"/>dirt, and cryes for helpe from thoſe that paſſe by.</p>
            <p n="88">88. How can wee paint Gods face, when MOSES, the man that euer was moſt familiar with GOD, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſaw but his backe parts.</p>
            <p n="89">89. Put caſe, the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:8022:43"/>
               <hi>Croſſe</hi> had a <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue</hi> of doing mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles; as PETERS ſhadow had, yet doth it not follow, that it is lawfull to worſhip it, which PETER would neuer accept of.</p>
            <p n="90">90. If the <hi>Pope</hi> may erre a as <hi>Man,</hi> but not as a <hi>Pope,</hi> I
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:8022:44"/>would know why the <hi>Pope</hi> doth not inſtruct or reforme the <hi>Man,</hi> or wherefore the <hi>Man</hi> doth not require the <hi>Popes</hi> inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</p>
            <p n="91">91. They are fooles, who becauſe it is ſaid, Examine your ſelues, and come, will not commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:8022:44"/>till they bee as they thinke perfect; forgetting that CHRIST came into the world, not for the healthfull but ſicke, and that we come vnto that Table, to bee refreſhed with that Spirituall foode, bringing nothing with vs but a
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:8022:45"/>purpoſe to amend.</p>
            <p n="92">92. Many doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue themſelues, in ſaying, they care not for the <hi>Father</hi> or <hi>Mothers</hi> Curſe (ſo they deſerue it not;) But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware, you muſt not inuert the order of Nature, in iudging your
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:8022:45"/>Superiours, chiefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in your owne particuler; For e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, the bleſſing or curſe of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, hath a Profitique power ioyned with it.</p>
            <p n="93">93. Beware of ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and lying, though but in ieaſt; For oathes, are but an vſe,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:8022:46"/>vſe and a ſinne cloathed with no delight or gaine: and therefore, the more vnexcuſable euen before men.</p>
            <p n="94">94. The <hi>Deuill</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer aſſailes a man, except hee finde him eyther voyde of knowledge, or of the feare of GOD.</p>
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:8022:46"/>
            <p n="95">95. If a <hi>Man</hi> ſhall once take vpon him, to call that light, which GOD calls heauie, that ſinne <hi>Veniall,</hi> which GOD cals <hi>Grieuous,</hi> meaſuring any one ſinne by the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of his luſt and appetite, and not of his <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> what ſhall
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:8022:47"/>let him to doe with the next, that his affections ſtirre him to, the like reaſon ſeruing for all, and ſo goe forward till hee place his whole corrupted affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in (GODS) roome.</p>
            <p n="96">96. As none can bee Schollers in a
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:8022:47"/>Schoole, and not bee ſubiect to the Maiſter thereof, ſo none can ſtudie or put in practiſe the Circles and art of <hi>Magicke,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Committing any horrible do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſection from GOD.</p>
            <p n="97">97. <hi>Treaſurers</hi> and <hi>Vſhers,</hi> are Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:8022:48"/>hated in Court; becauſe of neceſſity, they muſt giue Denialls and Diſgraces.</p>
            <p n="98">98. The <hi>Honour</hi> of a <hi>King,</hi> ſtands in the multitude of the People, and his ſtrength and ſafetie, in the <hi>Loue</hi> of his Subiects.</p>
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:8022:48"/>
            <p n="99">99. They are not fit for the Court, that are eyther ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate in Opinion, or vncourteous in Carriage, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, the noble minde is moſt fit; For they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes more cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, to take things in good part, then the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:8022:49"/>baſer ſort.</p>
            <p n="100">100. Euery age breeds ſome exorbitant Spirits, who turne the edge of their owne ſufficiencie, vpon whatſoeuer they can Deuoure in their ambitious apprehenſions, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king rather a great then a good Fame, and holding it the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:8022:49"/>chiefeſt Honour to bee thought the wonder of their times, which if they attaine vnto, is but in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, that are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired, but more abhorred.</p>
            <p n="101">101. <hi>Friendſhip</hi> is of that nature, as it
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:8022:50"/>alwayes deſires to bee entertained with mutuall good offices, therefore we muſt not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it to growe cold, for coldnes is a Degree of Deadnes.</p>
            <p n="102">102. They that are to make demaunds or requeſts to their <hi>Friends,</hi> muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:8022:50"/>how the ſame may ſtand with the ſafetie of their <hi>Friends,</hi> that their motions and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts may ſtand with their honour and ſuretie to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord vnto it.</p>
            <p n="103">103. The cauſe of Aſſembling all <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments,</hi> are two, for <hi>Lawes,</hi> or <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney;</hi>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:8022:51"/>The one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſinewes of <hi>Peace,</hi> the other of <hi>Warre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="104">104. Good purpoſes, aſwell in <hi>Princes</hi> as priuate <hi>Men,</hi> haue many hinderers; therefore, when the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie or Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodities of ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king or refuſing are once throughly
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:8022:51"/>weighed, a ſpeedie reſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is the beſt to cut off ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueniences, that delay of time com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly bringeth.</p>
            <p n="105">105. As the Naturall bodie is delighted in Change, ſo is alſo the Politique bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die greedie of Alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
            <pb n="98" facs="tcp:8022:52"/>
            <p n="106">106. As a whole man meanely able, may doe as much as a halfe man better able; So an inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our wit bent and Conuerſant vpon one ſubiect, ſhall many times with patience and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, diſſolue and vndoe many of thoſe knots and
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:8022:52"/>doubts, which a greater wit (diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with many matters) would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Cut in two, then vnknit.</p>
            <p n="107">107. Such as are bent to hold with the Difficulties of ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting any thing, are Commonly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it.</p>
            <pb n="100" facs="tcp:8022:53"/>
            <p n="108">108. Many neglect the wiſdome to maine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine themſelues, that GOD hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vpon them, and ſo worthily ſuffer by their own follie.</p>
            <p n="109">109. In Ciuill Actions hee is the greater and deeper Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, that can make
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:8022:53"/>other men the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of his will and ends, and yet neuer acquaint them with his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; So as they ſhall doe it, and yet not knowe what they doe; Then he that imparteth his meaning to thoſe that hee imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:8022:54"/>
            <p n="110">110. GOD made <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi> pure mindes bodyleſſe, <hi>Beaſtes</hi> bodyes mindeleſſe, but Man both bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and minde the Horizon betweene both.</p>
            <p n="111">111. Errours by miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking ſhould not bee too rigorouſly cenſured, but er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:8022:54"/>that bee wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, ſhould not bee ſpared.</p>
            <p n="112">112. The dutie of a Magiſtrate, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in three eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall points, in <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, Teaching,</hi> and <hi>Iudging,</hi> that he be <hi>Wiſe</hi> to <hi>Gouerne, Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous</hi> to giue <hi>Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> and <hi>Impartiall</hi> to <hi>Iudge.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="104" facs="tcp:8022:55"/>
            <p n="113">113. It is not fit that any thing ſhould ſucceed well with the wicked, for it is a puniſhment of his fault.</p>
            <p n="114">114. As it is a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Nature,</hi> that <hi>Putrifaction</hi> is more contagious before maturitie then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſo it is a poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:8022:55"/>of <hi>Morall Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophie,</hi> that men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoned to vice, doe not ſo much corrupt manners, as thoſe that are halfe good &amp; halfe euill.</p>
            <p n="115">115. The end of mans Creation is not for the ſlaughter nor e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation of Armes, to make men caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awayes.</p>
            <pb n="106" facs="tcp:8022:56"/>
            <p n="116">116. Vertuous Men will vſe their edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation military, as wiſe-men doe their weapons, for or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament amongſt their <hi>Freinds,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies for <hi>Defence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="117">117. Thoſe Actions that are intended for <hi>Opinion,</hi> are car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:8022:56"/>with more ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonie, then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie.</p>
            <p n="118">118. <hi>Dolus verſatur in generalibus,</hi> Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals dwel too much in the ayre; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, hee that will not bee deceiued muſt deſcend to particulers.</p>
            <p n="119">119. When IVPITER
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:8022:57"/>ſpeakes, hee vſes to <hi>Ioyne</hi> Thunder to it; So a King ſhould not ſpeake, except hee main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it by Action.</p>
            <p n="120">120. CHRIST recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends vnto vs, the wiſedome of <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents,</hi> not thereby to Deceiue or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray others, but to arme our ſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:8022:57"/>the Deceit and treaſon of <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="121">121. There is a <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen</hi> and a <hi>Hell, Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mium &amp; Paena,</hi> for the Elect and the Reprobate; but how many other roomes there bee, we are not on <hi>Gods</hi> Counſell.</p>
            <pb n="110" facs="tcp:8022:58"/>
            <p n="122">122. <hi>Prayer,</hi> is one of the worthieſt Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons wee doe; for wee ſpeake with GOD, and as it were enter in a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning with him, it brings downe GOD from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, &amp; makes him to grant our will, and dwell with vs and wee with him
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:8022:58"/>Eternally.</p>
            <p n="123">123. Of Temporall goods, wee ſhould pray only for thoſe that are neceſſarie, for our being; or at leaſt wel-being, and not for thoſe things, that are for <hi>Luxurie</hi> and <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluitie;</hi> for ſuch, are commonly baites to ſinne: But if
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:8022:59"/>GOD grant vs al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo theſe, we ſhould be thankefull, and ſoberly vſe them according to our calling.</p>
            <p n="124">124. It was neuer found, that blood and too much ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, did good in matters of <hi>Religion;</hi> GOD neuer Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to plant the
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:8022:59"/>Church by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</p>
            <p n="125">125. The whole Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, chiefely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth two things, a <hi>Command,</hi> and a <hi>Prohibition,</hi> to doe ſuch thinges, and to abſtaine from the contrarie; it is our Dutie to obey in both.</p>
            <pb n="114" facs="tcp:8022:60"/>
            <p n="126">126. It becomes euery Officer and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander, to know what belongs to his place, &amp; not to encroach vpon his Superiors, ſo ſhall good order be beſt kept in a great Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie.</p>
            <p n="127">127. In two Degrees ſtandeth the whole
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:8022:60"/>ſeruice of GOD by <hi>Man,</hi> interiour vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward by <hi>Prayer,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriour or downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward by <hi>Workes</hi> flowing ther-from, before the world.</p>
            <p n="128">128. Hee that nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth a faction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween his ſeruants in his owne family, doth nothing elſe, but helpe to ſet his
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:8022:61"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:8022:61"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:8022:62"/>owne houſe on fire.</p>
            <p n="129">129. Although a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>King</hi> is ſent by GOD for a Curſe to his people, and plague for their ſinnes; yet, it is not lawfull for them to ſhake off that Curſe at their owne pleaſures, that GOD hath laid vpon them.</p>
            <pb n="117" facs="tcp:8022:62"/>
            <p n="130">130. The ſafeſt guard a <hi>King</hi> can haue, is the <hi>Loue</hi> of his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, his greateſt honour, their proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritie.</p>
            <p n="131">131. As <hi>Law</hi> is to a well gouerned Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, ſo are good orders in houſehold gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, without
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:8022:63"/>which, no houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold can ſtand.</p>
            <p n="132">132. <hi>Heauen</hi> is gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by order, &amp; all good <hi>Angels</hi> there; nay, <hi>Hell</hi> it ſelfe, could not well ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt without ſome order: and the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Deuils</hi> are deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into Legions, and haue their Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines; how can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:8022:63"/>Societie then vpon earth, ſubſiſt without order or Degrees.</p>
            <p n="133">133. Though MO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SES were inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, inſpired, and Conducted, by Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty GOD him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: yet, he refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed not the good Councell of IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THRO for the
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:8022:64"/>manner of his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerment, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Almightie GOD allowed in him.</p>
            <p n="134">134. It is a certaine rule in all darke <hi>Propheſies,</hi> that they are neuer clearely vnderſtood til they be accompliſhed.</p>
            <p n="135">135. Many reſpects may Lawfully let
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:8022:64"/>in Admiſſion, that will not be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent cauſes of Depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</p>
            <p n="136">136. No wiſe man can think him a fit man to Counſell him, or to gouern vnder him, that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne himſelfe, and his owne Familie; and therefore, BA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SILIVS aduiſed his
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:8022:65"/>Sonne to take ſuch Counſellors, who had giuen proofe and experience of their wiſedome in the good Conduct and Direction of their owne affaires.</p>
            <p n="137">137. <hi>Emulation</hi> is the baite of <hi>Vertue,</hi> for looking into the ſweetnes of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, men vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:8022:65"/>takes the Labour.</p>
            <p n="138">138. It is leſſe difficult for perſons of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different eſtates, to make their choiſe of Friends, then for Great men; yet, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſafe to Pouertie; For there hee muſt bee in Loue with himſelfe, or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
            <pb n="124" facs="tcp:8022:66"/>
            <p n="139">139. Better it is that matters be not ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at all, then after they be once a foot and in motion, to giue the <hi>Truth</hi> leaue to lye gaſping and ſprangling vnder the violence of a Forraine faction.</p>
            <p n="140">140. Sometimes there is as good vſe, to be
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:8022:66"/>made of diſhoneſt, as honeſt Friends; for Poyſons are as neceſſarie as whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Simples, if they bee in a hand able to prepare them.</p>
            <p n="141">141. Suggeſtions are needleſſe from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, when the miſchiefe is felt at home.</p>
            <pb n="126" facs="tcp:8022:67"/>
            <p n="142">142. Although parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular men of all profeſſion of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, haue beene ſome theeues, ſome murtherers, ſome traitors; yet euer, when they came to their end and iuſt puniſhment, they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſed their fault to be in their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and not in
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:8022:67"/>their profeſſion; the <hi>Romaine Catholiques</hi> onely excepted.</p>
            <p n="143">143. The friends of a priuate <hi>Fortune,</hi> are leſſe dangerous; in greater, there is more gaine, and ſo more loſſe: He that ſtands without, ſtands naked, and ſubiect to euery ſtorme: who vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derpropped
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:8022:68"/>ſo long ſafe; but no ſooner looſened, but rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            <p n="144">144. To anſwere an improbable imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, is to fight againſt a vaniſhing ſhadow.</p>
            <p n="145">145. It is a true ſaying, that alleaged kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vpon noble
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:8022:68"/>mindes, doth euer worke much.</p>
            <p n="146">146. Too much ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition begets trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherie, and an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate <hi>Beliefe</hi> is dangerous follie.</p>
            <p n="147">147. For a little mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, a man may haue more from the <hi>Pope,</hi> then euer GOD promiſed by
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:8022:69"/>his grace to grant; a remiſſion of all ſinnes paſt and to come.</p>
            <p n="148">148. Preſent croſſes, are but preparatiues to them wee may feele.</p>
            <p n="149">149. Let no man thinke that hee may frame and make his wife as he pleaſeth, that
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:8022:69"/>ued SALOMON, the wiſeſt King that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer was.</p>
            <p n="150">150. Although we are not ſtockes nor ſtones, not to feele Calamities; yet, we ſhould not ſuffer the feeling of them, ſo to ouer-rule and aſtoniſh our rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as it may ſtay vs from taking the
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:8022:70"/>beſt reſolution, and vſing thereof for remedie that can be found out.</p>
            <p n="151">151. Age is venerable, not in reſpect of the apparance, but in reſpect of the annexion; becauſe, Wiſedome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies ſuch a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</p>
            <pb n="133" facs="tcp:8022:70"/>
            <p n="152">152. The <hi>Deuils</hi> are like the <hi>Peſt,</hi> which ſmites thoſe ſureſt, which flies it fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt &amp; apprehends deeplieſt the perill thereof.</p>
            <p n="153">153. ALEXANDER was not thanked &amp; commended for Conquering the World, but for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:8022:71"/>it before Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie yeares old.</p>
            <p n="154">154. It is the greateſt decay to Youth, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther not to indure good aduice, or not to beleeue it, vntill their perill and ouerthrow make them ſee it to their ſhame.</p>
            <p n="155">155. It is no power in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:8022:71"/>in the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, or in the holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of names of GOD vſed blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly, nor in whatſoeuer rites or ceremonies, that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can raiſe any infernall Spirit, or limit him perforce, within or without ſuch and ſuch Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles; but it is the craft of the <hi>Deuill,</hi>
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:8022:72"/>the father of lyes, who hauing firſt of all preſcribed that forme of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, faining him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to bee co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and reſtrained thereby, will bee loath to paſſe the bounds of thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunctions.</p>
            <p n="156">156. Continuall expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience proues, that
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:8022:72"/>
               <hi>Idleneſſe,</hi> is euer the greateſt ſpurre to <hi>Lecherie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="157">157. <hi>Man</hi> being Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded of all the foure Complexions (whoſe father are the Elements) al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though there bee a mixture of them all in all the parts of the Body, yet muſt the diuers parts of
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:8022:73"/>this <hi>Microcoſme</hi> or little world of ours, bee diuerſly more inclined, ſome to one ſome to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther complexion, according to the diuerſitie of their vſes: that of thoſe Diſcords a perfect harmony may bee made vp, for the maintenance of the whole body.</p>
            <pb n="139" facs="tcp:8022:73"/>
            <p n="158">158. He is ſaid rightly to ſerue his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, whoſe body executeth what his wiſdome plotteth.</p>
            <p n="159">159. Common affabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie is commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and not to bee miſliked, ſo it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the ſtate of the partie; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, it is not Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:8022:74"/>but Baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p n="160">160. Sauces, are more like medicines then meate, &amp; they ſerue onely for pleaſing of the taſte: and not for ſatisfying of the neceſſitie of nature.</p>
            <p n="161">161. Wee owe all men Salutation and a
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:8022:74"/>cappe, but not fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliaritie; For, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept wee bee ſure, their worthines de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues it, we betray our ſelues.</p>
            <p n="162">162. Whatſoeuer GOD doth by a <hi>Medium,</hi> muſt know an end; what immediately, belongs to eternity.</p>
            <p n="163">163. The Slaunderer,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:8022:75"/>and he that deſires to heare lyes, are whelpes of a litter; the one hath a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill in his tongue, and the other in his eares.</p>
            <p n="164">164. <hi>Fortune</hi> hath no power ouer <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> but of ſenſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, and of liues that ſwimme and Nauigate without
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:8022:75"/>the loadſtone of diſcretion &amp; judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p n="165">165. The diſpoſition of wicked men are peruerſe, <hi>Coaction</hi> muſt force them to goodnes, and <hi>Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> reſtraine them from wickednes.</p>
            <p n="166">166. <hi>Mans</hi> happines doth reſt in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:8022:76"/>of his owne time, ſo that euery man may be bleſt and rich in perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, if his owne diſſoluteneſſe, and vnthriftineſſe, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curres not the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie.</p>
            <p n="167">167. All qualities with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the direction of Vertue; profit not, but ouerthrow
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:8022:76"/>their poſſeſſors.</p>
            <p n="168">168. When the mouth of LAZARVS was ſhut, his ſoares ſpoke for him; ſo when wee cannot vſe our hands in defence of our Country, we ſhould lift them vp for our Princes protection.</p>
            <p n="169">169. If he be to be pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:8022:77"/>that beſtowes halfe his patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in Hobbie-hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> much more they, who hauing but a little time dedicate halfe to <hi>Sleepe</hi> and <hi>Idlenes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="170">170. As <hi>Troubles</hi> come for exerciſe of <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue,</hi> and increaſe of <hi>Merit,</hi> ſo <hi>Affliction</hi> ſends many to <hi>pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi>
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:8022:77"/>and <hi>faſting,</hi> and few men ſeldome doe well, except neceſſitie inforce them; for Hunger &amp; Pouertie makes men induſtrious, &amp; the Lawes make them good.</p>
            <p n="171">171. As the ſeruants of GOD are known by Humilitie and Charitie, ſo the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:8022:78"/>of the <hi>Deuill</hi> are knowne by Pride and Crueltie.</p>
            <p n="172">172. The Confeſſion of our ſinnes doe no leſſe honour GOD, then his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is blemiſhed by Commiſſion.</p>
            <p n="173">173. Suſpition is no where ſo conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant and powerfull
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:8022:78"/>as among <hi>Princes,</hi> vnto whom to ſay rightly, it rightly belongs: For how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they are, they haue enemies; if Good, enuious, if Euill, ſome that lay hold vpon that oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion; yea, euen their friends are doubtfull, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eaſie to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, whether lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:8022:79"/>of themſelues or of their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes.</p>
            <p n="174">174. To pray to the Lord with the lips for any Corporall benefit, and yet to haue the heart fixed in confidence of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny natural meanes, is a kind of ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Adulterie.</p>
            <pb n="151" facs="tcp:8022:79"/>
            <p n="175">175. He that is not a <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> gouerns by gueſſe, and will proue a dangerous ſtateſman, for whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vncontrouled affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions meete with high <hi>Fortune,</hi> they commonly begin <hi>Tyrannie</hi> and <hi>Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="176">176. The difference
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:8022:80"/>betweene the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and vngodly, is, that GOD doth vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit the vngodly by puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, names of Plagues, Curſes, and Deſtructions, as the Plague of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> the Curſe of CAINE, the Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>Sodome;</hi> but the righteous, when he doth viſit them, his puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:8022:80"/>corrections, chaſtiſements and roddes, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction not Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, to purge them, not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them.</p>
            <p n="177">177. It is not ſufficient for him, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready hath enough to defend him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Baſeneſſe</hi> and want,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:8022:81"/>onely to eate, and drinke, and make an euen reckoning at the yeares end: for, that is baſer then baſeneſſe, no? Let him doe his Country ſeruice, &amp; purchaſe honour to his Houſe; for wee are not in the world for fruition, but for Action.</p>
            <pb n="155" facs="tcp:8022:81"/>
            <p n="178">178. There is no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betweene comon Louers, and common Whores, they both flatter, and make the name of <hi>Loue</hi> their <hi>Bauds,</hi> to ſerue their parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer pleaſures.</p>
            <p n="179">179. As <hi>Mans</hi> nature is not only to ſtriue againſt a preſent
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:8022:82"/>ſmart, but to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge a paſſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie; So wee ſee, that <hi>Malice</hi> hath a longer life then ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Lioue</hi> or <hi>Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe</hi> hath: For, as alwayes we take more care, to put off paine, then to enioy pleaſure, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, the one hath intermiſſion, and with the other wee
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:8022:82"/>are ſatisfied; So it is in the ſmart of iniuries, and the memorie of good turnes; <hi>Wrongs</hi> are written in marble, <hi>Benefits</hi> are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, requited rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
            <p n="180">180. Almeſdeeds me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit nothing at Gods hands, yet they
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:8022:83"/>make him our deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor according to his gracious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe.</p>
            <p n="181">181. Preſumption is euer apt to drawe comfort, from the vaſt ocean of appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite; But Diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, from the ſweet ſprings of oportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie.</p>
            <pb n="159" facs="tcp:8022:83"/>
            <p n="182">182. Hee Councells beſt, that preferres the cauſe of GOD, before any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler.</p>
            <p n="183">183. Where Good-men are afraid, to call a <hi>Vice</hi> by the proper name, it is a ſigne that the vice is common, and that great perſons (who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="160" facs="tcp:8022:84"/>it is not ſafe to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger) are infected therewith.</p>
            <p n="184">184. He that knowes not the true grounds of an euill cannot helpe it but by change, which is a Dangerous guide of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth.</p>
            <pb n="161" facs="tcp:8022:84"/>
            <p n="185">185. <hi>Conſcience,</hi> not grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded on know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, is either an ignorant Phanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, or an arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant Vanitie; in one extremitie the <hi>Papiſts</hi> erre, in the other the <hi>Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="186">186. Correction with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our inſtruction, is
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:8022:85"/>meere <hi>Tyrannie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="187">187. GOD which is the great <hi>Lawma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker,</hi> by his <hi>Lawes</hi> preuents ſinnes; to the end, that pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments may be inflicted on it iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as to auoyd <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrie,</hi> hee forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth making of <hi>Images; Hee that cannot liue Chaſte let
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:8022:85"/>him Marry, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="188">188. Falſe <hi>Miracles</hi> and lying newes, are the foode of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, which by credulitie De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ludes ignorant peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p n="189">189. GOD who cals his Elect vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, to make them enioy Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:8022:86"/>compels none to make defecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from himſelfe: <hi>Nam perditio tua, ex te Iſraell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="190">190. <hi>Time</hi> the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, will bring foorth <hi>Veritie</hi> her Daughter, in due ſeaſon to perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p n="191">191. <hi>Riches</hi> are deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:8022:86"/>of wiſe men, onely to keepe them from baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe <hi>Charitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="192">192. A good <hi>Paſtor</hi> is the Phiſition of the <hi>Soule,</hi> and ought to apply his Doctrine ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe or hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi>
               <pb n="166" facs="tcp:8022:87"/>for want of which Diſcretion, ſome mons zeale hath done hurt.</p>
            <p n="193">193. It is a point of wiſdome to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne the Truth with as little Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation as may bee, loaſt a good Cauſe bee mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with ill hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</p>
            <pb n="167" facs="tcp:8022:87"/>
            <p n="194">194. The beſt <hi>Lawes</hi> are made out of thoſe good Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto the people is naturally inclined.</p>
            <p n="195">195. Groſſe and bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh errours, are ſooner reformed, then meaner e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcapes, for ſo much as the one cannot
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:8022:88"/>bee defended with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Impudencie, whereas the other admits ſome Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour for excuſe.</p>
            <p n="196">196. It is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to vſe vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full inſtruments, were it neuer for ſo good a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; for that <hi>Ax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iome</hi> in Diuinitie is moſt certaine and
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:8022:88"/>infallible, <hi>Non eſt faciendum malum, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vt bonum inde eueniet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="197">197. <hi>Valour</hi> is ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but being too much prized, it turneth to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridled furie.</p>
            <p n="198">198. To beſtow be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites of the Bad maketh them
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:8022:89"/>worſe, and vili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth the reward of the Vertuous.</p>
            <p n="199">199. <hi>Clemencie</hi> is a <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine</hi> inſtinct, and worketh Superna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall effects.</p>
            <p n="200">200. By the <hi>Deuils</hi> meanes, <hi>Deuils</hi> can nouer bee caſt out; and therefore they are fooles, who
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:8022:89"/>to cure a Diſeaſe caſt on by a Witch, ſeeke the helpe of ſome other Witch, whereas Prayer &amp; amendment of life is the onely Cure.</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
